[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is Sutta on the seven awakening factors.
[SPEAKER_01]: It begins, when a bhikkhu is accomplished in virtue, composure, understanding, and who has full knowledge and free, freedom, the sight of them is very helpful.
[SPEAKER_01]: To hear them, to approach them, to respect them, to recollect them,
[SPEAKER_01]: And why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because after hearing the teaching of such renunciants, a renunciant will live withdrawn in both body and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it continues, as they recollect and think about that teaching, at such a time, a renunciant has obtained or activated the awakening factor of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: They develop it and perfect it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are collected.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're established in the right context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you wouldn't be able to think about the particulars of the teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, if I...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I meet some... you meet someone who's a... who's... has... who's understood the dhamma, and then you reflect on that teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have the awakening factor of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I'm thinking about the teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if you are thinking about the actual teaching, in other words, if you understood them correctly, then yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, thinking about the dhamma is not an enlightenment factor.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, thinking about the information you have on dhamma, that's not the same as understanding the meaning, the core of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, if you understood the dhamma, then, when you think about it, the enlightenment factors will be brought to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you haven't understood the dhamma for yourself, you can think about the dhamma all you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: About it, it won't be on the level of enlightenment factors, because it's not on the level of insight.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but before we get into discussion, what are the enlightenment factors?
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness, and then
[SPEAKER_01]: dhamma-vicāya, investigation into dhammas, effort, joy, calm, composure, and equanimity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Equanimity, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's... yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the first thing, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the... see... and that's kind of the problem with most of the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Things you read in the suttas, it's that... it's been so long ago, since they were taught, they were remembered.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only way to remember those things was through these, like, linear lists, like 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, or 4 of this, or 8 of that, or 12 of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people then be... and that's just mere information.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just... just pure information.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only seven enlightenment factors to somebody who doesn't have a clue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody who is enlightened, he doesn't even need to... he doesn't...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like the important thing to realize.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's exactly the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, as many so to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like the right view and right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, whether it's the right effort through that, it's right because of the right view and the right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's the right speech through that, it's right because of the right view and right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like this right view comes first, and then, mindfulness through that is right, and the direction of your effort is right, or your livelihood is right,
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not like I develop the right view, then I go for the second step.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a step-by-step arrangement.
[SPEAKER_00]: And neither is seven enlightenment factors, which is exactly... See, he goes and hears the wise people.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands what they teach.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he actually understands.
[SPEAKER_00]: He develops... he becomes a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: He develops the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, on the basis of that correct view, standpoint, when he thinks about dhamma, when he is mindful, those enlightenment factors develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not by not having the right view and thinking about the list of enlightenment factors.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, if I do these things, these seven things, they will lead me to enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I do step by step these seven steps, it will culminate in complete enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I have no clue
[SPEAKER_00]: What that enlightenment is, I have no right view in regard to the, you know, escape from suffering and where the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll just basically use the information that I have on the level of lists, and collections, and steps, and methods, and instructions, and I'll adhere to it with, like, hopefully, it will kind of bring me the result.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as the opening video read, it already says, no, first you need to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, these factors will come to fulfillment and development.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, without understanding, without a right view, there are no seven enlightenment factors in you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how much you think about them.
[SPEAKER_00]: If, on the other hand, you don't think about them as this methodical, list-by-list, step-by-step instructions,
[SPEAKER_00]: But actually, try to understand the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is correct mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the correct investigations of phenomena?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the correct effort?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is samādhi?
[SPEAKER_00]: Samādhi comes just before equanimity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, here I am, believing I can practice samādhi even without the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: There will somehow result in enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as an enlightenment factor is just one towards... just before, like, calling
[SPEAKER_00]: I have not properly fulfilled samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there are all these things that I need to develop beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that you can infer from reading the sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ah, have I developed all these things beforehand?
[SPEAKER_00]: Have I truly developed the right view that then makes me correctly mindful, that then makes me correctly thinking about the dhammas, that then brings the joy and calm and so on?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or am I just fabricating joy or hoping for a calm
[SPEAKER_00]: As a kind of magical result of my method, of my technique, so that I don't have to drill the work and go through the painful process of trying to gain the understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so these factors are factors of an awakened person, that he's developed, the awakened person is developing these factors.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, these are factors, again, like many other things mentioned in the suttas, are the factors for somebody who has the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody who knows what... how to get to the end result, how to... how to fully achieve enlightenment, but hasn't done it yet, so these factors are the factors that he should dwell on and contemplate, and... and they will come to fulfillment if he just follows the direction of his own right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the usefulness of why the Buddha listed these seven factors is for those who have kind of attained to the right view, but haven't completed the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a good reminder to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, look, it's only these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are seven aspects of the same thing that you already have, that you already understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: That already freed you partially.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, dwell on these seven aspects and they will in return basically bring other aspects to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember first coming across it and trying to do these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you sitting there meditating, whatever, watching the breath, and then you try to look for those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm making an effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I'm investigating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel quite calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, I'm peaceful, so... Oh, he somehow composed a samādhi?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, look, although it's very close to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, just keep it going, and then... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that is... that is sort of the... quite... like a normal, especially, you know, due to the whole, like, Abhidhamma stuff and commentarial, where the whole dhamma is presented as just basically a collection of lists and... and myriad of, like, information and this and... and parallels and... and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But none of that is actually the d
[SPEAKER_00]: Without that, there is no dhamma, even if you know all of the suttas by heart, and all of the information you've collected.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's something that people don't necessarily know, because, again, you know, you're presented with so much stuff today, and so many different texts, so then you come to... you come and read various things, and then you immediately, naturally, sort of, try to make sense out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you... you're not aware that you're actually reading into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not... you're not... you're not transparent enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have the right basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have the gradual training developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you come across this information, you're kind of taking it as information that's being misunderstood for understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And most people's understanding is that, just a collection of information.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when they sort of
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a form of understanding, but it's not a form of understanding that pertains on that individual, personal level, internally, to be known by the wise, as the Buddha says.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, the one that pertains to freedom from suffering, for which no amount of information will suffice to free you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only that insight into Four Noble Truths would.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the important thing to realize.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't have the right view, that must be your your sole kind of goal, is to develop right view, insert into freedom from suffering, to know for yourself the origin, the suffering, the origin, the cessation, and the path that leads to cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when that's understood, then, within that understanding, you have the right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the Seven Enlightenment Factors.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the Four Right Strivings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whichever aspect you put, it's within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, through developing this one insight and state of mind that I have, that I kind of work for, I am developing this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, if you want to develop it more,
[SPEAKER_00]: Astutely, more precisely, more efficiently, you then study further the information about the seven enlightenment factors, so that you can apply it correctly within that basis that you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't have the basis, it's just a collection of information.
[SPEAKER_00]: And dangerous in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very dangerous, because information is just too easy to be misconceived, confused, mistaken for understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, when you have so much information or, like, the... Again, I don't want to sound out too much, like, too much thinking or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or too much information is bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's dangerous because of the wrong attitude underneath.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, whether you have the information or not, the wrong attitude is really what keeps you ignorant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, don't think now, like, that if you are getting...
[SPEAKER_00]: I must not get all this information because it's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your ignorance is dangerous, so you have to always keep perspective in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I am ignorant and I'm collecting information now, I'm learning about the suttas, I'm not taking anything for granted, I'm taking everything with a pinch of salt, until I know for myself the way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the only criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing shorter than sotāpatti should be a criteria of success.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't have that authentic attitude,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, whether you have a little bit of information or a lot of information, well, it makes no difference, because you're already obscured by yourself, by being ignorant, by not having that right attitude, that pertains to freedom from suffering, as the only measure of understanding, not the satisfaction of, you know, making the sense out of information and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll just continue as the first one.
[SPEAKER_01]: As they recollect and think about that teaching, at such a time, a renunciant, with the right view, has obtained the awakening factor of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: They develop it and perfect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when they investigate and explore and inquire into their teaching, wisdom, at such a time, they have that awakening factor of
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, see, another aspect of that is that all the enlightenment factors are kind of peripheral, secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he investigates, the mindfulness gets developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he thinks and ponders about that teaching he understood, dhammavīcāya, it gets developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not, he thinks about dhammavīcāya and that's how dhammavīcāya gets developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: He thinks about the dhamma, ponders on dhamma, or fortifies his understanding of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: That effort is the development of dhammavīcchā, secondarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't think about dhammavīcchā.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you know, I think about dhammavīcchā now, and that's dhammavīcchā, and I see dhammavīcchā being developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he clearly says that.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he does this, mindfulness gets developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: While he's doing this, dhammavīcchā has developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so, as he investigates
[SPEAKER_01]: Indirectly, again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, striving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: While he's making the effort to clarify what he understood, to fortify, to sustain, to protect that context, everything we talk about, all that, that he invests in that, brings the the enlightenment factor of effort to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not, oh, I shall fulfill this effort towards enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he's striving.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's striving towards the goal of freedom from suffering that he understood but hasn't fully fortified.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, the direction of the right view, the understanding that you get through the right view, the effort you're putting into furthering that understanding is the enlightenment factor of effort and striving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and then he's attained that enlightenment factor of joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, joy arises on its own, as a result, as a product of his... As a by-product, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like, oh, I shall be joyful and now let me bring this joy now, because that's another factor that the Buddha talks about.
No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Follow the direction of the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't fall from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't neglect it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't become negligent or complacent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Joy will arise on account of the effort that you invested in following that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when that mind is joyous, the body and mind become calm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unified and calm.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, that's not something he does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me... let me unify this now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me fulfill that which understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me dwell further on the understanding of the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me fortify them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that will calm down your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will establish samādhi like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the establishment of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not the, oh, let me directly attend to this that will concentrate my mind on account of my effort to concentrate my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely... You say, go in the direction of that right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, go in the direction of the right understanding, the right view, which is the right mindfulness, the correct investigation of phenomena, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that results in composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: towards that direction, being fully committed, directed, composed, uh... in... in that one way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that's one-pointedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not one-pointedness of your tip of your nose or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's one-pointedness of the direction towards freedom from suffering, composed in that one direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like one way only, for the one who practices rightly the satipaṭṭhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no right view
[SPEAKER_00]: No enlightenment factors, no right view, no samādhi, no right view, no freedom from suffering, no understanding, no wisdom, no equanimity.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you think you have samādhi, and you think you have equanimity, and you think you have joy, without a right view, knowing that you don't have the right view, take them with a pinch of salt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognize that they might not be the one, the correct.
[SPEAKER_00]: Samādhi and correct equanimity, because there is no right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not to say, oh, there is no samādhi at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no form of samādhi at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, it's important to recognize that the wrong samādhi, mistaken to be the right samādhi, cannot magically become the right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only fully abandoning that with the samādhi of the wrong kind that you have, the equanimity and peace of the wrong kind that you have, fully abandoning it, in order to get the right view,
[SPEAKER_00]: Through exposure of that recognition to, you know, towards suffering and so on, that's how you can get, then, the right samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sometimes people might think, oh, well, you know, I know my samādhi is not right, but if I keep investing any effort in this wrong samādhi, it will become right.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right samādhi is the result of right view and correctly directed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right samādhi is not the result of repairing the wrong samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking you can directly attend to your samādhi as a form of concentration that will then result in some liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, you don't concentrate your mind there towards your own concentration and develop your samādhi through focusing and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You develop samādhi by following the right view, which is sort of guided by the right mindfulness and correct investigation of the factors, and joy, and calm, and effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that becomes a unification of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's equally secondary, the right smādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's indirect.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... it's basically peripheral from where you are making your effort towards understanding freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... it's... this whole section is found in Majjhima Nikaya 117.
[SPEAKER_01]: These three states run and circle around
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's always those three.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have the right view, means there is a degree of right effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there certainly means there is a degree of right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have right mindfulness, the right view is there, and right effort is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have right effort, the right view is brought back, and the right mindfulness is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not linear.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you try to understand them on the level of their linear information, you will fail.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they cannot be attended to directly, and be understood in their nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can attend information directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, there's one, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what does that information pertain to?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, pertain to... pertains to understanding freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: What suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, suffering that I'm liable here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of me making the effort to make... to sort of draw connections and parallels that nobody else thought of, and somehow get a magical insight on account of it, between these seven factors, let me dwell... dwell on the level of my liability to suffering, endure it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't try to get rid of it or manage it, which is why you always try to jump and pounce on the information, hoping it will bring you freedom, because you want to get rid of the liability that is painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the efforts to understand the dhamma, if they're directed towards basically manipulating and sort of drawing parallels between information that you collected about a dhamma, it's just going to become another form of management.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, you need information.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to be told what to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you refuse to allow yourself, basically, to come back onto the level that it matters, where that applies, you're just gonna stay on the level of playing with information for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you refuse to give up the attitude of trying to manage your liability to suffering by understanding information.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's psychotherapy, that's psychology, that's any kind of worldly way of dealing with suffering and pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all on the level of management.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's only relatively efficient.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you learn the seven factors, you learn the Four Noble Truths, you learn the gradual training, you have more information than you need.
[SPEAKER_00]: As we said before, back in the Buddha's day, there were no sutta collections.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the information we have now, on account of the, you know, the nikāyas, like, monks did not have access to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only Ānanda remembered all of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most of the monks didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And probably, vast majority of them knew maybe one story, with one instruction, and that was enough for enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you know the Four Noble Truths, you know the gradual training, most importantly, you know what comes first, virtue, sensory strength, guiding of the sense doors, you have all the information you need.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you have to start doing that which that information tells you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the catch.
[SPEAKER_00]: People don't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when they take on the virtue, take on the gradual training, they kind of still keep it on the level of performing the instruction gain on the level of information.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they don't want to endure
[SPEAKER_00]: The dukkha, on that right level, that liability to suffering, they don't want to feel it without immediately trying to manage it, because it's too unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you just give up the management and just stay under that pressure of that unresolved liability to suffering on the most, on the deepest existential level.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have to, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the right view were to sort of
[SPEAKER_00]: Take the root and start to grow.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can only do on that basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody... well, he teaches only two things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody correctly understands the nature of dukkha, there are only two outcomes of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either mental derangement or noble search.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, okay, this, if they don't lose their mind on account of the recognition of that correct pain of liability to suffering, that existential dread,
[SPEAKER_00]: If they don't lose the mind on account of it, then they will have no other choice but to try and correctly uproot it and seek the correct information.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will then, sort of, you know, be the basis for them making the right effort and enduring things on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it comes down to that, enduring things on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you endure things on the level of that existential dukkha without trying to manage it, get rid of it, distract yourself from it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the whole basis for the right view and everything else that comes from it is being developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's that fundamental difference between information and understanding of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's two opposite directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, information gives you something that needs to be understood, but only your effort to understand can bring that understanding, not more information.
[SPEAKER_00]: More information cannot accidentally result in understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only your effort to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, most of the monks didn't have 99% of the suttas that we have today.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in a way, see, that was good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Their minds were less cluttered with so many information.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, with that natural tendency to draw parallels between information, instead of understanding each and everyone individually on that personal basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like when a person reads about nāmarūpa,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, reads about the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, tries to understand how nāmarūpa relates to five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, drawing parallels between, develops the belief that, oh, see, I understood this now, because, look, I found the common ground, the connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, that's just a connection of further information.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were truly authentic, the way I'm talking about, if you endured the suffering on the right level, nāmarūpa, or the five aggregates, or the six sense bases, doesn't matter which one,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to understand nāmarūpa, to the extent that frees you from suffering, or at least offers a direction of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you need to understand the five aggregates, to the extent that frees you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or saḷāyatana, to the extent that frees you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not, hmm, nāmarūpa relates to the five habits, which is all on the basis of... All of that came much later, when people have all this information, and fell away from that personal basis of recognition of their own liability to suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, it's just too easy to start conflating information and connection between information with, like, greater understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, got even worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: People started studying Pali scholastically,
[SPEAKER_00]: And in learning the etymology of the informational term, develop the belief that you understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you truly understood viññāṇa, for example, you'll be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the Buddha said, complete understanding of viññāṇa means arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all of that, it doesn't matter how much information you have, and how much... how dependent you became on that information, all of that can be cleaned away.
[SPEAKER_00]: In one sweep of just re-establishing yourself, if you're brave enough and strong enough to endure it, on the level of, I am still liable to sickness, aging, death, anxiety, dread, suffering, I know no escape from it internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am not able to not move when these things present themselves, which is why I always try to avoid those things from presenting themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: I always try to cover up when they're present.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the possibility of their presence, I always try to ignore and distract myself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you abandon these attitudes, and endure these things on the right level, even the little information you collected, will start slotting itself in the right place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now, you got the basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the two factors for the right view, it's, yes, correct information, utterance of another, and yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without it, there is no right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you listen to the Buddha himself giving you information.